<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2014) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2014) -->

<section anchor="sec:control" title="The Control Protocol">
  <t>
    In Section 12.2.6 of <xref target='RFC5661' />, the control
    protocol is introduced. There is no specification of a control
    protocol, and indeed there need not be such a protocol in use
    for any given implementation, but a set of requirements
    are provided to describe the interaction between the MDS
    and the DS, For the purposes of this draft, there are three
    broad requirements of such interactions:

    <list style='format (%d)'>
      <t>
        NFSv4.1 clients MUST be able to access a file directly through the
        MDS and not the DS. I.e., the MDS must be able to rerivie
        the data from the consituent DSes and present it back to
        the client via normal NFSv4.1 operations. Whether the MDS
        allows access over other protocols is strictly an implementation
        detail.
      </t>

      <t>
        The MDS MUST be able to restrict access to a file on the DSes
        when it revokes a layout.
      </t>

      <t>
        The DS MUST honor the byte range restrictions present in the
        layout. I.e., if the layout only provides access to the first
        2 MB of the file, then any access after that MUST NOT be granted.
      </t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    There are some notable absences from those broad requirements:

    <list style='format (%d)'>
      <t>
        The enforcement of
        authentication and authorization so that restrictions that would be
        enforced by the metadata server are also enforced by the storage device.
        Examples include both export access checks and if the layout has an iomode
        of LAYOUTIOMODE4_READ, then if the client attempts to write, the I/O may be rejected.
        <vspace blankLines="1"/>
        While DSes should make such checks on the layout iomode, <xref target='RFC5661' />
        does not mandate that all Layout Types have to make such checks.
      </t>

      <t>
        The allocation and deallocation of storage. I.e., creating and deleting files.
      </t>
    </list>

    <cref anchor='AI1 ' source='TH'>
      This lack of MUST on LAYOUTIOMODE4_READ sounds bogus. Why wouldn't all Layout Types do that?
    </cref>
  </t>
</section>
